William Fonds Provenance
CUPCAKE CORNERS HISTORICAL SOCIETY
Papers of William Fonds Provenance 1917-1955
Cupcake Corners Historical Society
Provenance, William Fonds, 1897-1956
1.6 cubic feet (4 boxes)
Correspondence, diaries,and writings of an archival theorist and author documenting his experiences in World War I, his literary endeavors, and his ideas on modern archival theory, especially regarding the centrality of the fonds.
Mss 2 A
Biography of William Provenance
Archivist and author William Fonds Provenance was born at Last Chance, Nevada to Fred and Mary Jones Provenance on January 4, 1897. Little is know of his early life prior to serving in World War I as an ambulance driver. After graduating from Freen College in 1924 with a degree in cryptogamic biology, he first followed a career in commercial horticulture and later worked as an itinerant archivist. Provenance also had a lifelong interest in creative writing, producing both novels and poetry. He died at Frostbite Falls, Minnesota, March 15, 1956.
Scope and Contents of the Papers
The collection consists of diaries, correspondence, manuscripts, and miscellaneous materials documenting the literary and archival career of William Fonds Provenance.
The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence, principally with his mother, other archivists and writers. His diaries describe his experiences as an ambulance driver in France during World Was I in vivid detail. It also includes manuscripts of novels, poetry, and essays on archival theory as well as the final draft of his seminal work, Quarks: The Tao of Archival Descripton. Many of Provenance's ideas about archival description were thought by his contemporaries to have been obscure or naive. A contemporary reexamination of his theories, however, reveals that in many respects Provenance's ideas were insightful and highly nuanced.
Major correspondents represented in the collection include Ernest Hemingway, F. Scott Fitzgerald, Arthur Miller, H.L. Mencken, Theodore Schellenberg, Ernst Posner, and Provenance's long-time companion Ima Gusdorf.
Organization of the Papers
This collection is organized into three sections:
Correspondence
Diaries
Novels, Poetry, and Essays
Related records
The papers of Ima Gusdorf are located in the Freen University archives.
Separated materials
The James Joyce Collection at the Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas-Austin, contains correspondence from Provenance to various French literary publications regarding Joyce.
Other Finding Aids
A partial index to Fond's correspondence, prepared by Ima Gusdorf, is available at the Cupcakes Corners Historical Society.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog of the Cupcake Corners Historical Society. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Persons:
Fitzgerald, F. Scott (Francis Scott), 1896-1940; Fruin, Robert, 1857-1935; Posner, Ernst; Gusdorf, Ima May; Hemingway, Ernest, 1899-1961; Mencken, H.L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956; Miller, Arthur, 1915-; Schellenberg, T.R. (Theodore R.), 1903-1970
Organizations:
Freen University. Center for the Study of the Giants of Archivy; United States. Army--Transport of sick and wounded.
Subjects:
Cataloging of archival materials; Diplomatics; United States -- History -- World War, 1914-1918 -- Personal narratives, American
Places:
Frostbite Falls, Minnesota
Document Types:
Diaries; Novels; Poetry
Titles:
Quarks: The Tao of Archival Descripton
Restrictions on Access
This collection is housed in off-site storage. Twenty-fours advance notice is required prior to research use.
Custodial History
Following his death, Provenance's papers were bequeathed to his brother Harry who attempted several times unsuccessfully to sell them to a private collector. Upon Harry's death, the papers became the property of Provenance's literary executrix and longtime companion Ima Gusdorf who donated them to the Freen University Center for the Study of the Giants of Archivy.
Acquisition Information
Acquired as a gift from Ima Gusdorf, December 17, 1952
Detailed Descripton of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Correspondence, 1919-1955., 8 folders
  Incoming letters and copies of outgoing correspondence with family, business associates, and prominent archivists and writers. Letters are arranged alphabetically by the writer's or recipient's name.
  - A-D (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - E-F (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Gusdorf, Ida, 1942-1955. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - H-M (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - N-P (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Provenance, Mary Jones, 1931-1942. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Schellenberg, Theodore (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - T-Z (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Diaries, 1917-1918., 32 v. in 5 folders
  Daily accounts of Provenance's experiences during his military service in France during World War I, primarily documenting the daily activites of camp life, weather, military battles, and operations of the army medical service. Also contains detailed and graphic accounts of his work as an ambulance driver.
  - 1917 (Box 3, Folder 2-4)
    - January-March (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - April-September (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - October-December (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1918 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
    - January (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - February-June (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Novels, Poetry, and Essays, 1947-1954.
  Published and unpublished writings of Provenance. All the materials are typescript, though most also include handwritten annotations. Some of text appears to have been deliberately obliterated, perhaps posthumously. The materials are organized into three groups by genre or subject matter: poetry, novels, and works relating to archival science.
  - Poetry, 1948-1952. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Verse in various forms, principally sonnets and limericks. The sonnets contain detailed dedications either to Provenance's mother or to an unnamed "dark lady." Many of the limericks are ribald in their subject matter.
  - Novels, 1947-1955., 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Manuscripts of three unfinished novels, each apparently written in the style of an author Provenance admired.
    - For Whom the Chimes Toll, in the style of Ernest Hemingway, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - The Great Gaspar, 1953. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Barchester Cathedral, 1954. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Works on archival theory, 1947-1955. (Box 4, Folder 2-4)
    Two unpublished essays and the complete manuscript of his book-length work, Quarks: the Tao of Archival Description. Internal evidence within the collection suggests that this work may have been self-published though no copy of such an edition has been found in his papers.
    - The Effects of Disintermediated Access on Archival Cataloging, 1946 March 17. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - The Centrality of Provenance, 1951. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Quarks: the Tao of Archival Description, 1952. (Box 4, Folder 4)